Okay, this is the latest episode of Concord Storytellers, take two.
We just tried recording and one of the microphones decided not to work, so we are back at it.
And I have today, again, a special guest.
I was saying before, I'm waiting to have just sort of an average Joe guest, but today, this
does not qualify.
I have Amity Wilczek here.
Amity, please let us know.
Give us your 30,000 foot view of the life and times and we can go on from there.
Sure.
My name is Amity Wilczek.
As you mentioned, some people know me also as Mickey Wilczek, my middle name, Mickalena,
and for my very strong minded and strong tempered, impressive, great grandmother, Italian grandmother,
Mickalena Kona.
I am trained as an evolutionary ecologist and had a career in both research and teaching
as an evolutionary ecologist, transitioned a few years ago to more applied work.
I now work for the federal government, specifically for at the Volpe Center, which is part of
the Department of Transportation doing climate analysis and policy work.
Awesome.
I think that, well, a few things.
One, you are my number one draft pick in life.
If the apocalypse hits and we have to live off the land to survive, I'm coming straight
to you.
I want to say that.
Because you've had a really, I think that you must have a really hard time doing two
truths and one lie when you're doing social interactions.
Because you can tell three truths and zero lies and they're all sound like lies.
Can you think of the top three coolest things you've done?
I have my own list.
I want to see how much it coincides.
The top three, if you did two truths and one lie, but they were all truths, what would
they be?
Okay.
So a few truths about myself.
It's not that unusual that you have to say, have to come up with something, tell us something
about yourself that no one else knows or that no one in this group knows.
So one of the things I often say is that I have worked as a sheep midwife on three continents.
So that is true.
Another thing I have done is for over the span of about 10 to 15 years, I was a natural
history lecturer on tours of various locations, particularly islands.
And in fact, two different trips that were islands of the world by private jet.
So I've been to a lot of islands that are off the beaten path in my lifespan and I hope
to go to many more.
And let's see, what is a good third one?
Let's start with those two for now.
Okay.
Maybe we'll get to the third one.
Yeah.
I think, well, I think we're going to do a deep dive into deep springs.
I think there's probably about 30 things from there from life at deep springs that could
probably qualify.
Before we jump into that, can you talk about your ties to Concord?
My ties to Concord.
So I moved here almost exactly four years ago now and it's been wonderful.
This was not my first time living in Concord, however, fairly randomly I ended up being
a high school student for all four years of high school at Concord Academy.
My first year I was a day student taking the train every day from Cambridge.
And then the last three years my parents moved away.
I think they were hoping I was going to move with them, but I kind of secretly applied
to be a boarding student.
I had other ideas.
We moved around a lot and I liked Concord.
I liked Concord Academy a lot and I wanted to stay.
And they were kind enough to recognize my intention there and to honor it.
So I then was a boarding student for three years.
That's cool.
And loved it then.
I walked around many, many a weekend.
I would spend an entire day walking through Concord, which was fun then.
And now it's spectacular.
There are so many more established trails than there were when I was a high school student
here.
Trails and benches that you found, correct?
Benches, yes.
Yes.
The Concord Bridge, our local newspaper, did a wonderful story that led to a long-lost
bench being rediscovered.
But this was something, yes, before this became a story in the Concord Bridge, we had mounted
our own campaign to locate all of these bicentennial commemorative granite brentas that the Concord
Garden Club had put up.
We first encountered one in the cemetery and it was just very strange because it said sort
of, it said 1775 to 1975 and we were sort of, what did this bench live for 200 years and
then die?
Because there was no context.
It just had these dates on it.
So then we suddenly saw some others around town and it became a puzzle to figure out
where they came from, how many there were.
Turns out there are 10, one of which had fallen into the ground but is now being put back
up.
Well, I have some news for you, you may not know.
Part of the initiative of the 250th is that we're going to be some new benches.
Really?
Yeah.
Oh, I have some thoughts about where that's supposed to go.
Okay, oh, interesting.
Yeah.
We connected with the committee and I just learned that very recently so I was like,
oh, I know some people who are going to be very interested in this.
Oh, yes.
So we've known each other for a while now.
How long has it been?
It's close to 20 years.
It's getting a lot, yeah.
Okay.
We have a lot in common.
Same birthday.
Same birthday, coming up.
Yeah, coming up.
That's A. We're going to go all the way to double Z on December 20th.
Yeah.
On something we have in common and we're doing this at 3 in the afternoon.
We're enjoying some nice seltzers.
I think it might have been more appropriate to do this at about 8 at night with a bourbon.
But we have both been sued.
Oh, yes.
Something I want to get into, that's sort of the lead that we'll get to with Deep Springs,
but not personally sued.
We've both led organizations that have been through lawsuits and anyone who hasn't been
through that, I'm sure personally it's even more harrowing.
But even when you're part of an organization and you're just representing an institution
and not yourself, it's an experience.
It is life.
It just absolutely upends your life for the duration of the whole thing.
It's kind of wild.
Mine was, I remember the first day of business school, I went to the entrepreneurship class.
They said, hey, if you start a business, as soon as you get past 30 people in your company,
you're just going to start getting sued by people who come out of the woodwork, people
you've never heard of.
It's just what happens.
It's part of the game.
I thought, that's kind of crazy.
There's no way.
Sure enough, it just starts happening.
People you've never heard of just start suing you over weird stuff.
Yours is way more interesting though, because I think even starting with the beginnings
of how you got to Deep Springs all the way through to when you left, it saw some major
change and you helped lead the school to that change.
Maybe we could just start at how you found Deep Springs, what Deep Springs is, and what
drew you there in the first place.
Yeah, absolutely.
While I was at Concord Academy, my first time here in Concord, I did spend one semester
away at what was then a new program called Mountain School, which is in Vermont.
It's a one semester program for high school students that is both... It's a sort of a
farm school.
It's a school and a farm.
It's unusual.
It's a very environmentally centered education, but it's also unusual in that it really allows
its students more responsibility than your typical high school would and asks them to
participate meaningfully in a lot of decisions as well as responsibilities in running the
school.
Making sure at that time a lot of the facilities were heated by wood.
We would literally have to fell trees and chainsaw them up and chop them up and feed
them to the dragon, which is what we call a giant wood burning stove.
It was an incredibly life changing, meaningful experience for me being up there, being with
these other students, these other young people who were so interested in sort of jump starting
their career as adults and being treated like adults.
Being given those responsibilities and opportunities and also just that connection to living in
a place and having a better sense of what it took to actually run the whole school and
being able to see all of that.
I loved it.
It was there that I first heard about another institution called Deep Springs College, which
was college rather than a high school.
It was spoken of at the mountain school as being somewhat of an inspiration and a like
minded institution.
Deep Springs takes it to another level in terms of the degree of student participation.
The other thing I learned about Deep Springs immediately was that it was only for male
students, that it was not a coeducational school.
There was no possibility I could go and there was no similar school that admitted women.
That was that.
I sort of followed that away.
If that had been available to me, I definitely would have applied.
I went to University of Chicago, which ended up being a great place for me in all kinds
of ways.
No sour grapes there, but it had definitely stuck with me that I was interested in it.
Went on, got my PhD, was doing really intense ecological research that took me.
I had five different field sites in Europe that I was visiting from near the Arctic Circle
up in Finland to the Mediterranean coast and everywhere in between.
Really all in on the research.
Part of that project was I had students working with me at each of my field sites.
Throughout my graduate student career and that research career, a lot of the experience
I found most rewarding was really working closely with the students.
I was recognizing that education was something important to me.
When I was starting to think about faculty jobs, I was looking at complete opposite ends
of the spectrum.
I was looking at ones that were completely research focused.
Then I was looking at smaller rural arts schools, places that were much more teaching focused.
I thought to myself, hmm, now I know Deep Springs doesn't admit female students, but
I know women work there on the staff and as teachers.
I wonder where the heck is going on with Deep Springs and if they might be looking for professors.
I went and looked and sure enough, they were hiring a science professor.
This might be my chance to check out Deep Springs and get there a completely different
way.
So I applied.
That was not the normal way, especially for long term professors.
Certainly at that time, a lot of the people who came to Deep Springs as professors had
already been there for the long term professorships, had been there as visitors before or had some
direct experience.
I didn't know anyone there.
I was basically cold calling.
I still sort of in a way, I sort of can't believe that I made it onto the radar, but
I went out there and it instantly, two things became very clear to me.
One was it was going to be a fascinating place to be a science teacher and to be a science
educator and would be like no other opportunity I would have.
The other one immediately, I did not go into it thinking, hey, I want to make this place
coeducational.
I haven't been into it very much.
I want to see what Deep Springs is like.
But I would say very quickly, my experiences there, I shouldn't say instant, but very quickly
it became very clear to me that there was something really missing from the students
experience because they have so much power and responsibility there.
Something was really missing from their experience in excluding half of the world's population,
especially since the mission of the school is to prepare, at that time it was to prepare
young men, now it's to prepare young people, not to jump the shark, but to prepare young
people for a life of service to humanity.
If you're preparing for that and off the bat excluding half of humanity from participating
in that work, it's a limited experience.
Sure.
Yeah.
My understanding is that out there, like you were saying, it's to another level.
You're not just chopping down wood to heat the place.
You want food, you're growing your own food.
You want a steak, go get the steak.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
I used to tell you processed cows?
Yes.
One thing I do want to say is Deep Springs is not wholly self-sufficient in terms of
the food it produces, but at least when I left, it was wholly self-sufficient in terms
of all the meat that it produced and all of the eggs and all of the dairy.
That fluctuates over time depending on the student interests and the staff availability,
but it certainly was when I left.
Well, I remember during COVID, you describing what it was like there.
Yes.
In the country, it seemed like one of the safest places to be in the world because you
had some touch.
I remember you saying you did have some suppliers coming in and you had very strict protocols
with what you did when you got deliveries and what you did with the materials, what
they came.
Yeah.
But I mean, this is self-sufficiency has its advantages.
It does.
Yeah.
And it's very isolated too.
The school is located in a high mountain valley in Eastern California, almost on the Nevada
border.
The school's at about a mile elevation.
It's in a basin.
There's nothing in the basin but that school.
So you have to go over a mountain pass and over an hour in each direction to get to a
town.
And it's not like the nearest towns are particularly bustling and huge.
So it's quite isolated.
But yes, in terms of the meat, yes, Deep Springs is another level.
Yes, I did participate.
I did not actually ever directly kill any of the large animals while I was there, but
I definitely helped break them, what we call break them down.
It's a nice euphemism, but empty out the guts and butcher them.
For a cow, that's not something that happens that same day.
That's a big task.
That's a huge animal.
That takes some time to do that.
So I definitely helped with that.
That was not an expectation of my job.
That is an expectation of the students.
This was really more.
Yeah, but you wanted to understand the whole experience there.
I did want to understand the whole experience.
And it was an amazing, this was one of the things that was so fabulous about teaching
at Deep Springs was, you know, there were especially, you know, as a scientist, there
were all these opportunities.
So I taught a course on vertebrate functional anatomy, which is sort of looking at an animal
and understanding something about its lifestyle from the way that it's built.
So you can tell if an animal is likely eating, has primarily a plant-based diet or primarily
a meat-based diet based on its teeth and its stomach and things like that.
So for that course, we went to a cow slaughter and emptied all the guts into a front lobe,
not to get too gross, and then rooted through them.
I think people should know what happens when they're eating a burger.
They should know how it gets there.
Yeah, and the students had to, you know, go through this front loader bucket and identify
everything and see how it was all connected and look on the outside and the inside and
what was in there.
It was extraordinary.
Yeah, it was a really fabulous experience.
And yeah, so there was the meat grown there.
We had a lot of, it was a combination of growing on land, growing meat animals on land that
the college owned and also farmed for hay for the animals, but also grazing on public
land.
So a lot of work I did with the students also was working with all the various government
agencies and some additional organizations that were interested in the environment around
there to really monitor range health and animal health and make sure that, you know, really
understand what it meant to be involved in being stewards of the land in this tradition.
So that was, it was really wonderful.
And the students at Deep Springs, you know, they're not just, there's this mystique of
it as the Cowboy College, and that certainly is true.
Every student there has the opportunity to learn how to ride a horse, you know, in the
Western tradition and chase cows on horses and all that, which is something I actually
love to do.
But the students were also, and importantly, involved in writing the application for the
other students and evaluating.
Not only were they involved in that, they headed it.
You know, faculty and staff were available as advisors, but we're not the final deciders
on this, a lot of this.
Yeah, I'd say that I think it's great how much opportunity you give students there for
administrative, leadership, management type tasks.
Because one thing I noticed in my business career, and I think of it is once you become
the person who's in the room leading a meeting, leading discussions, deciding tasks, things
like that, you don't know everything.
You're going to make mistakes.
Like, you're going to mess some stuff up.
And you can immediately tell the people who have never had a leadership position, who
don't empathize, who basically will just attack you if you say one wrong thing or if you,
you know, if you just, I don't know.
I think having at that young of an age responsibility that's meaningful on things that actually
have an effect on the community and to understand what that means, how that feels, what it looks
like.
When I've met students of yours who are in their early 20s, they are some of the most
mature people that I've met.
And it's pretty incredible to me how level headed they are.
And just it's like they are, they seem to have much more experience than the people
of their typical age.
Absolutely.
And one of the experiences I think that Deep Springs really offered them that's valuable
and is not, it's hard to come by for young people these days.
And particularly, I would say, super high achieving young people is the ability to fail.
You know, we, you know, we sort of, we put them in situations that they weren't fully
ready for and asked them to step up to it.
And you know, I don't mean a failure that you can't recover from, but give them that,
I mean that in the positive sense of identifying growth opportunities.
Sure, yeah.
You know, there were, there were people there to help them and to help them work through
it, but they weren't, the safety net was loose, was there, but it was, it was not keeping
them in place.
They could fall into it.
And some of that, you know, and also some of it was, I mean, I was, I was saying Deep
Springs is not totally self-sufficient, but you know, there was no, we had faculty advise,
faculty and staff advisors who were in charge of some of the maintenance work, but the students
did all the cleaning, the dishes, you know.
And so there was a lot of, a lot of emphasis on that as well, that, you know, being a leader,
having a role in the community, taking part in the community is not just a sort of the
glamorous executive tasks.
It's everything.
And I think of, so you know, Congressman Andy Kim is a Deep Springer who most, probably
what most people recognize him for is his, the pictures that were taken of him, the,
on January 7th, the day after the, the Capitol uprising where he was cleaning up trash in
the rotunda.
Yeah.
You know, he showed up early and he just started cleaning up trash and people were so struck
by that, but I saw that and I was just like, there's a Deep Springer.
There's a Deep Springer, you know, he doesn't expect it to be someone else's job, right?
If you see it and it's your, it's in your view, why not do it?
And so, you know, I think that is a really, that's a really important piece of that too.
That it was, it was very gratifying to me that so many, that act resonated with so many
people, but it also to me just seemed like so obvious.
It was not, you know, that he would have done that because that's exactly the kind of thing
that, yeah, that the students at Deep Springs do.
Yeah.
I love that.
So you joined as the science professor, the science faculty.
Yes.
You became dean.
I became dean, yes.
How did, how did the idea of going, I'm sure the idea had been talked about over a long
time there, probably even before you got there, but how did the idea of making the student
body co-ed, how did that come up and how did it actually get turned into action?
Yeah.
So, I mean, it had been discussed literally for decades before I even arrived.
And it was a decision that was lay in the hands of the trustees.
So the decision was actually made soon after the trustees took a vote, I think it was 12
in favor and two not in favor of transitioning to co-educational student body just a couple
of, within a year or two of my arriving there.
And so that was, that was in the works.
It wasn't entirely my decision.
They did, the trustees did an enormous amount of work sort of studying this and thinking
about what would, what was the history of the school?
What was the intention of the founder?
You know, really trying to honor their work as trustees.
Most of them came to the conclusion that this decision they were making was, would be in
support of what the founder was trying to do, which was primarily establish a special
mode of education, not primarily establish a place for young men.
Right.
Okay.
And, but there were two trustees, both of whom were alums.
They were, you know, there were more alums who voted in favor than not, but two of the
trustees who were both alums voted against it.
So and they were the ones who then sued to stop the school from, from going, becoming
co-educational.
I would say also though, that we did as a faculty, the trustees asked us as a faculty
to write a letter, a position letter to give to them as they considered their decision
what they were going to, how they were going to vote.
And so we, we did, and we laid out our arguments and the faculty was unanimously in favor as
well of transitioning to co-ed, both because we felt like it served the mission of the
school and would be beneficial, directly beneficial to the education of the students to be in
the company of, of a more diverse peer group, but also because we felt it would elevate
the ability of the school to attract and retain good faculty.
I mean, I have to say I got a lot of, there were, there were plenty of people who couldn't
believe that I was teaching at an all male school.
Right.
Many of my, many of my friends that were saying, what, what are you doing?
You know, what are you doing at this regressive place?
Yeah.
And that's, but it's, yeah.
But you've, even before you were co-educational, you were still, even in a small student body,
bringing in people from all over the world and who went on to highly successful outcomes.
Absolutely.
So, I mean, it's, it's, it's prestigious before it's co-ed already.
Yes.
I just think it gets better as you add to the applicant pool, to the student body.
Absolutely.
Yeah, and I definitely don't want to denigrate the experience of any of the students who
went through when I was an all male student body.
I, you know, Andy Kim, there's so many, so many of the students, you know, my former
students that you've met were there while it was still all male.
They're, they're extraordinary.
I think they had an extraordinary experience, but the feeling was definitely that it could
get even better.
Yeah, places evolve.
I mean.
So, so that was, that was, that was in the works.
And then, so once the trustees sued to stop the school going co-ed, it then began a very
long legal process.
I don't think any of us realized how long it was going to be.
Right.
At the outset, it ended up going on for, I think, over six years in the end.
But we, it was an unusual, and I'm not a lawyer, so I can't speak to the details completely
accurately of it, but I can speak to my experience of it.
We got a really wonderful, really wonderful local judge was going to be the person hearing
the arguments because what was being the grounds for suing was there, some of the trustees
were trying to change the deed of trust, which was what, where this language of promising
young men came from.
So it was under this special trust law, which I think is much more conservative than a lot
of corporate changing laws of corporations, which is what most universities, what most
universities are so incorporated under.
So it was a different kind of case.
So the judge suggested that the lawsuit be tried in sort of three parts, the first of
which was, could the deed of trust be read as allowing interpretation of that language
to include people who are not men?
And then after that, he wanted us, if that one didn't succeed, then he wanted us to bring
forward a lawsuit saying, you know, would the purpose of the trust be served better
by allowing this change?
Right.
So the first trial was about whether the language could allow for that interpretation, that
you could admit women under the language of the trust.
And I think the non-descending trustees, so I'm just going to call the non-descending
trustees the college, but let's be clear, that's who we're talking about, really thought
that was going to go through.
They thought it was not going to be a difficulty.
But the judge disagreed and, you know, I think he was just trying, I don't know what went
on in his mind, but I think he was trying to be very careful.
Right.
And he was being very careful and strategic in the way he suggested this go forward.
But the experience of this was that it was extremely painful because we had thought this
was going to go through.
So we had gone ahead and started to solicit applications from young women as well as young
women.
We had even started to, so the application happens in two rounds, we had even started
to, I think, notify some of the young women that their application was progressing to
the second round.
And then that decision came in and not only that, but there was an injunction against
bringing any young women students on campus.
So it was extremely painful for a lot of people.
And we had to notify all of these young women that they were no longer invited to be part
of the application process.
That stinks.
And again, this was a communication that was, in the end, sent out by the students.
I mean, we helped them with it, we put it together, but it was heartbreaking.
It was very different from what we had hoped for.
If you imagine the first drafts were very different from the final draft.
Yeah.
And there were a lot of drafts that never made it to paper.
So that was very difficult.
But then there was the next stage, which was trying to argue that the purpose of the trust
would be better served by allowing the change to that language, to change the language from
promising young men to promising young people, for the education of promising young people.
And so that was an incredibly involved case that involved bringing together all kinds
of evidence.
So there were two women.
It was over a week long.
There were so many people called to speak.
There were two women, one of them was a hostile witness, and then there was me.
I mean, hostile witness, as in she was called by the dissenting trustees, basically.
She wasn't planning to come, but she had.
She had involvement with Dew Springs?
She had.
And her particular involvement had been that she had started.
So this is a really wonderful woman named Laura Marcus who continues to run educational
programs inspired by Deep Springs through an organization called Tidelines Institute.
But she had founded a program called Arte, which had been a summer program for women.
And it was very much inspired by the Deep Springs model.
And so anyway, they wanted to.
The dissenting trustees wanted to bring her in to, I'm not entirely sure actually what
they wanted to do, but they wanted to bring her in to raise the possibility that Deep
Springs, I think among other things, had been sort of secretly trying to educate women by
Laura Marcus had also had been a staff member at Deep Springs.
But that maybe Deep Springs had been secretly funneling money or some other things to Arte,
but it had not to this, to her All Women project.
But anyway, they were able to get through her testimony fairly quickly.
Then I was the other witness and I came for the majority of the trustees for the college.
And I spoke to, by that time I was a dean and I spoke to the letter that we had prepared
as a faculty.
I spoke to, I'm an environmental biologist, environmental biologist, ecologist, evolutionary
biologist, which also means I deal with very large complex data sets.
So I have to be a statistician.
So I do a lot of that work now on climate for the government.
But at Deep Springs, I'd also again through classes, again with students had done an enormous
amount of statistical analysis on the applicant pools.
So I also spoke to the one year that we had data from the women who had applied, I spoke
to the qualities of the applications we'd received from young men and young women.
And also spoke to my experience of the difficulty of recruiting and retaining faculty to teach
an all male student body, which was becoming, I mean, as you can imagine, it was becoming
increasingly more and more difficult.
So I spoke to all of those things, but it was a, being cross-examined was an unpleasant
experience.
Let's put it that way.
Yeah, no, absolutely.
Yeah.
You just, you asked a question and you're just like, wow, you just twisted some stuff
around on me there.
Yeah, exactly.
What are you doing?
Exactly.
Yeah.
I mean, I guess from my perspective, it sounds like an institution that started as someone
starts something and it's sometimes when you're writing these documents to start something,
someone who started something from a blank piece of paper, like you write some of these
documents and you put as much attention as you can into them.
But in the back of your mind, you're never thinking to yourself, this little thing I'm
starting is become some national or worldwide institution.
Right.
You're not planning that far ahead.
No.
You're just, I just want to make this work so that I can survive.
And then maybe we have something nice.
So I can imagine when Deep Street started, it's probably this local thing that it's probably
easiest to do if it is all men.
Because in my local population, there's only people who might be interested in it.
Yeah.
Well, it was also 1917.
Yeah, 1917.
I mean, there's how many, yeah, it was, you know, the idea of a women's college.
Your applicants won't even be able to vote.
Right.
Yeah, exactly.
Harvard, there's Harvard and there's Radcliffe.
I mean, it's like, it's, you just, you don't anticipate, you don't anticipate 100 years
ahead.
How can you?
And I think it's just interesting because Deep Springs became, it's a worldwide organization.
You have people from all over the world applying.
Yeah.
And there are things modeled after it that, again, when you start something smaller, that's
even modeled after something that you've got to put, you just have to put constraints on
it because otherwise, like being niche is something good to get when you're getting
started.
Yeah.
So it sounds like just probably one of the most incredible growing pains that could ever
happen for the institution.
Yeah.
But you were cross-examined, you made it through.
Made it through.
So this, that, that decision went in our favor.
And I must say it was also extremely gratifying.
So Laura Marcus, the other female witness that I was talking about, she had also wanted
to go to Deep Springs.
I mean, this is what started her on her journey of founding a Deep Springs like place was
that, you know, if Deep Springs wasn't going to educate women in that model, then by darn
it she would.
So, but the judge's decision actually featured me and featured Laura quite prominently and
said that, you know, our, our testimony and the fact that we had wanted to go to Deep
Springs showed materially the kind, you know, the loss of good candidates that they were,
you know, people they were excluding from the experience.
So that was, that was very touching.
Yeah.
That was really, that was, that was a reward for a lot of, for many years of heartache.
So even when we won that judgment, however, we still had to delay because the, the dissenting
trustees that appealed and having gone through that awful thing once of having to disinvite,
disinvite women, we did not want to go through that again.
So we wanted to wait till everything was fully settled.
But we went to, the appeals went the same way as the lower court.
I honestly can't remember if they tried to take it to the Supreme Court after that or
not, but if they did the Supreme, either way, the Supreme Court declined to hear it.
Whether, I think they did try and the Supreme Court declined to hear it.
So then they were, that was the end of it.
So it was one day and then it's over.
He says about six years from day zero.
Yep.
Till then you could open it up.
And the decision, the final decision on the appeals court, there was, because I said the
school was founded in 2017, in 1917 and 2017, and for years they've been planning a centennial
celebration and you know, hundreds, which is huge for Deep Springs.
Deep Springs is fewer than, because it's so small, I don't think we've talked about
this, but the school is maximum 30 students at a time.
And each student is only there for two years.
So it has fewer than a thousand living alumni.
So getting a couple hundred of them together is huge.
And especially in that tiny community that's usually, you know, fewer than 50.
Actually, yeah, so it was several hundred.
And we got the decision like literally within a week of that starting.
So it added a whole nother layer of celebration and excitement.
Yeah.
And an exciting future forward to look at.
So it was really wonderful.
So but it did come in in the summer.
So we had to decide whether to expedite the process and like just get started.
You know, the applications were going to be put out within the few weeks following that.
And we had to decide, are we ready to make that change right now?
Right.
Is there anything else?
And we just said, let's just do it.
So that time, we just said, we're going to do it.
We're going to open it up.
So this whole six years, while this is happening, are you also then still having trustee meetings
with all these people together?
And yes.
And then then it's over.
The decision is made.
And trustees get together again.
Oh, so that thing happened over the last six years.
Because trustee boards of trustees don't like they're pretty inert, right?
Like they don't change a whole lot.
They don't know.
So one of the trustees who was dissenting, I think, got off the board, rotated off the
board fairly soon.
But one of them was still on, I think, even through the, certainly through the first court
decision.
I can't remember if he was still on all the way through the appeals or not, to be honest,
at this point.
I think he was.
But so they were still around.
Yeah.
While this was going on, they were still on campus.
And it was, you know, it was, it was, I think it was personally uncomfortable for some,
for some people.
I have to admit after, after the really, I found personally, actually, my own personal
cross examination was a little bit unpleasant.
But there were other parts of that process that were really unpleasant and really made
it difficult for me to interact with the, at a personal level to interact with the,
with that trustee.
There were some, I felt really underhanded things done and some unnecessarily personal
attacks, not actually on myself, but on others, more important to the college that I really
found it hard to stomach.
But you know, it was, it was cordial enough.
And you know, I think, again, in a very deep, springsy way, when that trustee was, when
the one remaining dissenting trustee was still on the board, when there were board meetings,
at least once, if not multiple times, they were given the opportunity to meet with a
student body and sort of explain where they were coming from.
Right.
They asked for it and they were, you know, and the rest of the college said, sure.
Yeah, right.
This is, this is in the spirit of what we do.
Right.
Of discourse.
So that was, yeah, so, so it's, you know, I think it was cordial.
Yeah.
We tried to be, we tried to be, we tried to be adults about it.
But it was also difficult because that was, I would say, because of trial, because that
was going on for six years and students are there for only two, you know, for many years,
it was clear that whatever was happening with that court case was not going to directly
affect the experience of our current students.
So that was one of the few things where we didn't really, where the faculty or some of
the administration and faculty and staff were having a very different experience than the
students.
Sure.
Because we were trying to insulate them from that because it didn't, it wasn't going to
affect their experience, you know, of being a student at Deep Springs and we didn't really,
we didn't want it to.
Right.
It didn't, it, so, so there was, you know, that was, that was also, it could be a little
difficult to navigate at times.
Gotcha.
Cool.
Well, that is, that's an incredible story, an incredible experience.
And I mean, talk about leaving your mark on something.
That's pretty, that's pretty fantastic.
Yeah.
I'm very proud of you and I think I know your whole family is and.
Well, I'm just so pleased for Deep Springs.
I mean, I, so I did stay.
So I had, when I, early on in my time there, I sort of decided for myself that I really
wanted, once, once the trustees voted to make the school co-ed, I really wanted to stay
to see the first co-ed class graduate from Deep Springs.
So I made that sort of internal decision on my part and I did it.
It took a lot longer than I was expecting.
Yeah.
And it was delayed by six more years, which is a huge delay when you're talking about
living in a isolated valley than just a few other people.
I was there for 10 years in the end, but when the first co-educational class showed up and
the first women showed up, one of the, I was, it was, it was amazing to see.
And one of the things that was most, that made me feel like, two things made me really
feel like, okay, this, we've done our jobs getting this ready is that, you know, the,
I'm not going to say they didn't experience any hardships because I know they did.
It's always difficult to be one of the integrators, but, you know, the women students showed up
just wanting to be Deep Springs students.
They didn't want to be recognized as the first female Deep Springs students.
They were there.
They were there not to be, you know, they were there to be Deep Springs students and
they were, you know, they, they just, they took it on all of it.
They were, they were fully part of, of everything.
And then the other thing that I think was harder for some of the, some of the staff
and faculty who'd been really deeply involved with this court case for so long is that,
but I was, I mean, I'm not going to say it wasn't ever hard for me, but I was so proud
of them.
So that those young women did not want to hear, felt no responsibility, just be like,
thank you so much for all your, for not doing this.
You know, that was not their job.
Right.
And in fact, they really didn't want to be, to have to keep reflecting on that history
of all of the, you know, what had gone forward.
They were, they were in the moment of now of all the things that needed to be done to
keep the school running and to be students at that school.
Right.
Well, that's great.
So I was like, good.
That's, you know, good on them.
Yeah.
So let me just be a student.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
This is, this is what we wanted.
We wanted them to be students and that's what they're doing.
Well, that's excellent.
That's a great story.
I mean, I think timely for the current, the current times we're in and in the U S and
I think good model of, I think it's useful for people to hear just what it takes to make
that sort of change, which is at some level a pretty simple decision, but then the actually
making it happen is extremely complex and very time consuming and does not come without
fighting.
Yeah.
It doesn't come without fighting.
And I will also say, you know, it was, I want to give a shout out to, to the person, Dave
Hitz, who was the president of the board when this began, who also early on, you know, said
that he would personally finance any financial costs having to do with any lawsuit or any
additional costs that would go with, with going coed.
So that would not be part of the consideration of the trustee's decision.
He realized what he signed up for, but he did not.
He absolutely did not, did not back down on any of that.
And I think that, you know, that was, that was an incredibly, and he also has a deep
springs alum and I think that was an incredibly wise, very deep Springsy move on it.
He's like, let's, let's make sure this decision is about the, you know, on the principles
and the idea of this and that's what we get to do.
That's a huge pressure relief.
Cause I mean, I think without that, yeah, you always have in the back of your mind,
budget constraints and absolutely makes it easy to punt down the road.
Yeah.
And then possibly just never happen.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So he, and he, he, he did well by the, by his institution.
He made his institution proud.
Well, well, thank you so much.
I think we'll have to have you back.
There's there.
I think there's so many things we could talk about, especially I would say, I would love
to talk to you about, I say, since you were a high school student, you're like walking
through Concord and taking walks with you is interesting because I, when I go walking
in Concord, I don't see anything.
I just see plants and I don't know what any of them are.
So we should do another one with that.
And that would be great.
And yeah, we have, I have about, yes, eight more months to go to try to get to my 30 episodes.
So we'll, I'll be very happy to talk some more about any of the other many weird, wide
ranging experiences.
I thought that was cool.
I thought that was cool to share.
It's someone in Concord has done something historically significant and world changing.
So that's pretty incredible that, that we get to have you as part of the community here.
So thank you.
I'm delighted to be here and I'm excited to, to be in Concord for a while.
Awesome.
All right.
Thank you.